How did it all get there?
These are the opening words of a booklet
that was published back in 1950
and entitled Evolution versus the New World.
That booklet was just what our brothers needed at the time.
For example, in 1954, a man in Algeria
received a copy of the booklet from a friend.
He said, I devoured it.
And that booklet helped him to come to an appreciation
of Jehovah as his creator, and he became our brother.
Well, Evolution versus Creation is still an issue today.
And as touched on in some of our comments,
Jehovah's organization has provided additional tools
that help us both to strengthen our own faith
in Jehovah's our creator.
And also to help us aid others to come to know Jehovah
as their all-wise and loving creator.
These tools help us to follow the instructions
that are found in 1 Peter 3, verse 15.
Please open your Bibles to this scripture,
and as we read it, we'll notice two things.
First of all, the scripture encourages us
to make a defense for our faith, and then it
tells us the spirit in which we should make that defense.
1 Peter 3, verse 15 says,
But sanctify the Christ as Lord in your hearts.
Always ready to make a defense before everyone
who demands of you a reason for the hope you have,
but doing so with a mild temper and deep respect.
So there are two key points here.
First of all, we are expected to make a defense for our faith,
and that includes our faith in Jehovah as our creator.
Second, it tells us as we make that defense,
we should do it with a mild temper and deep respect.
Now, over the years, our message about evolution
and creation has not changed.
However, we have refined the methods
that we use to present that message.
The approach of the booklet evolution
versus the New World was very straightforward and direct.
And if you read it, you may say some parts of it
are even confrontational.
You can see that from the very title of the booklet,
evolution versus the New World.
Then on page three of that booklet, it says,
evolution and the Bible collide head on,
which survives the crash.
And it continues, evolution versus the New World,
which wins the war.
However, our discussions about evolution and creation
do not have to end in a collision
or going to war with the householder.
Really, what we need to do is establish
what are the facts and what do the facts reveal?
We may be surprised to find that there is even some common ground
that we have with those who believe in evolution.
For example, a witness student may read in his science textbook
claims that the earth and the solar system
are billions of years old.
Now, does this conflict with what the Bible teaches?
Not necessarily.
The Bible reveals that the earth and the solar system,
the universe, were in existence
before the beginning of the first creative day.
So these things could well be billions of years old.
What we need to do is determine the facts
and then base our conclusions on those facts.
And this is the approach that's taken
by two powerful brochures that we received back in 2010.
The one brochure is, was life created,
and the second, the origin of life,
five questions worth asking.
The approach of both these brochures
is positive and it's practical,
and they help us to answer the question,
how did it all get here?
For example, if we look at page two
of the was life created brochure,
under a heading entitled,
what is the purpose of this brochure?
It states the following.
It is not the purpose of this material
to ridicule the views either a fundamentalist
or of those who choose not to believe in God.
Rather, it is our hope that this brochure
will prompt you to examine again the basis
for some of your beliefs.
Then the brochure, the origin of life on page three,
says this.
Sooner or later, all of us need to confront the question,
was life created or did it evolve?
This brochure will present just some of the evidence
that has led many to believe that life was created.
There's nothing confrontational about this,
we're simply being encouraged to examine the facts.
And after we've separated the fact from the fiction,
then we want to determine exactly what are
the needs of the householder.
It may not be necessary for us to go into
a detailed discussion about DNA or RNA
or pro-cariotic cells.
Now if we have to explain those things,
we're grateful that we have these two brochures to help us.
However in many cases, a simple illustration
may be all that is needed to convince our listeners
of the existence of a creator.
For example, a missionary in Cambodia
took his camera to a motorbike shop
and he asked the owner of the shop
to spread out the metal and plastic parts
of a small motorbike on the floor of the shop
and the missionary took a picture of those parts.
Then he would show that photograph to a householder
and ask them,
now do you think all these parts can just come together
and become a motorbike?
And the answer is of course not.
But then he shows them a second picture
with the shop owner standing amongst the parts
and then he asks them,
now do you think these parts can become a motorbike?
And the householder smiles and nods
and he gets the point.
So usually we're not talking to staunch evolution
as people who make it their life gold
or promote evolution and discredit the Bible.
For the most part, the people we talk to
have had the theory of evolution thrust at them
all their lives and they just need to know
and learn the truth.
So the foundation of our belief in Jehovah
as our creator is solid, it's based on fact.
And that same faith convinces us
that the promises of a righteous new world will come true.
Evolution offers no such future.
So with full confidence,
may we continue to uphold the sovereignty of Jehovah
and his creation and may we defend our faith
by sticking to the facts
and then presenting those facts
in the way that is understandable to our listeners.
If we do this, they too will recognize the truth
of Genesis chapter one, verse one.
In the beginning, God created.